Well, I hope you're eager with anticipation for this session in JupyterLab as we finally get to see
JupyterLab의 이번 세션을 기대하시기 바랍니다 드디어 벡터를
vectors firsthand.
직접 보게 되니까요
So hopefully you are in the week five folder, you're in day three, and you're going to be following
여러분은 5주 차 폴더에 있고 3일째에 있습니다 어느 때보다
along with me more than ever.
저를 따라오게 될 거예요
It's important for this one because it's going to be visual, and you're going to get a real sense of
이 예제에선 시각적으로 중요하고, 실제로 어떻게 진행되는지 감을 잡을 수 있기 때문에 중요하죠.
what's going on.
Get it.
So this is just a duplicate of the previous day with more added.
이건 전날의 복사본에 더 추가된 거예요
So we begin with some imports, and now we've added to the imports to include some special things that
자, 가져오기부터 시작해보죠 가져오기에 추가된 것은 우리가 다룰 특별한 기능들이고요
Today.
오늘요
We're going to be importing OpenAI embeddings, which is part of Lang Lang chain OpenAI package.
OpenAI 엠디딩을 가져올 겁니다 랑랑 체인 OpenAI 패키지의 일부죠
We're going to be importing chroma from lang chain chroma.
랑 체인 크로마를 가져올 거예요
Um, and then there's a couple of things we're going to be importing so that we can have some fun and
그리고 불러올 것이 몇 가지 있어요 재미있게 실제로 이 벡터들을
actually visualize these vectors, something called t-SNE, which we'll talk about, and then something
시각화할 수 있도록요 t-SNE라는 거죠 나중에 얘기할 거예요 그리고
from Plotly that is going to give us some nice diagrams.
플롯리에서는 멋진 다이어그램을 줄 거예요
Let's do all of that importing.
불러오기를 해보죠
Okay, uh, let's run the constants.
좋아요, 상수를 실행해보죠
Bring in our environment variables.
환경 변수를 불러오는 거죠
This, of course, is now super familiar to you.
이제 아주 익숙해지셨겠죠
We're using the loaders to load in our knowledge base.
로더를 이용해 지식 기반을 실을 거예요
We're using the text splitter to create our chunks, of which there are 123.
텍스트 분할기를 이용해 덩어리를 만들 건데, 123개예요
And there's chunks for each of our four folders our contracts, products, employees and company.
4개의 폴더 각각에 구획이 있어요 계약, 제품, 직원, 회사
So I wanted to take one more moment to remind you about embeddings and auto encoding LMS that we've
한 번 더 삽입과 자동 역행 LMS에 대해 상기시켜 드리고 싶네요 지금까지 코스
been talking about auto regressive LMS in most of the of the course so far.
대부분에서 자동 역행 LMS에 대해 얘기했었죠
This is the first time we're going to look at auto encoding LMS that take an entire input and use it
자동 인코딩 LMS를 처음으로 살펴보겠습니다 전체 입력을 가져다가 하나의 출력을
to create one output, in our case, a vector.
생성하기 위해 사용하죠 우리 경우엔 벡터죠
And an example of an auto encoding alarm is Bert.
자동 인코딩 경보의 예가 버트죠
We're going to be using this one here.
이걸 사용할 거예요
OpenAI embeddings.
오픈아이 삽입구죠
Let's run that.
실행해 보죠
Okay.
네
So chroma is we're about to create our chroma data store.
크로마 데이터 저장소를 만들 거예요
And I've just put in this little section here to delete or empty the database if it's already there.
여기 이 부분을 집어넣었어요 이미 있는 데이터베이스를 지우거나 비우기 위해서요
Otherwise every time you run this code it adds in the vectors another time a sort of duplicate set of
그렇지 않으면 코드를 실행할 때마다 벡터가 추가됩니다. 벡터 모음이 중복되어서
vectors and things get confusing.
혼란스러워져요.
So this helps to refresh the database.
데이터베이스를 새로 고침하는 데 도움이 되죠
If you've already run this once and you can imagine I've already run this once or twice, so this is
여러분이 이미 한 번 실행했다면∙∙∙ 저도 이미 한두 번 실행했다고 상상하실 수 있죠 그러니
a useful thing for me.
이건 제게 유용해요
We will delete it.
저희가 지울게요
It's sitting in this folder here vector db um, which is just a db name, a constant that I set at the
벡터 db 음 이 폴더에 있어요 그냥 db 이름이죠 상수예요 DB 이름이
top to show you that I said DB name is vector DB.
벡터 DB라고 표시해뒀어요
It can be whatever you want and it's based on SQLite.
SQLite 기반의 뭐든 될 수 있어요
So if you go in here you'll see there's some SQLite stuff going on.
여길 보면 SQLite 관련 작업이 진행 중이죠
So it's just got a bunch of different files sitting within the name of whatever database name you chose
여러 개의 다른 파일들이 있는 거죠 여러분이 부여하고자 선택한 데이터베이스 이름
to give it.
내에요
In this case vector db.
이 경우엔 벡터 db죠
Okay, so it's time to create our vector database and populate it with our vectors.
이제 벡터 데이터베이스를 생성하고 벡터로 채울 차례군요
And I'm going to have another of those gradio moments here.
또 다른 그러디오 순간을 보여드리죠
You might think that the process of vectorizing a bunch of documents, turning them into vectors and
여러분은 문서들을 벡터화하고 벡터 데이터베이스에 저장하는 프로세스가
storing them in a vector database is something that would be reasonably sophisticated and would be,
꽤나 복잡할 거라고 생각하실 수도 있습니다 적어도 여러 개의
I mean, at least several cells.
셀이 있을 거라고 말이죠
But you'll find, of course, that we can do it in one cell and we can do it in one line of code.
물론 한 셀에서 할 수도 있고 한 줄의 코드에서도 할 수 있어요
And that is, of course, thanks to Lang Chain putting a lot of great glue code around this.
랭 체인이 접착 코드를 많이 발라서 가능했어요
It wouldn't actually be that hard to do it ourselves manually to iterate through, to turn each of these
수동으로 하는 건 그리 어렵지 않아요 반복하기 위해서요 이런 각각의
embeddings into each of these chunks into vectors, and then store it ourselves in chroma, it would
삽입을 각각의 덩크마다 벡터로 전환해 크로마에 저장하는 거죠 4,
perhaps just be 4 or 5 lines.
5줄이면 될 거예요
Um, but it's that much simpler if we can just do it in one like this.
이렇게 한 번에 하면 훨씬 간단해요
And the other great thing about this is that if you try different vector data store, it's the same
이것과 관련해 또 다른 장점은 다른 벡터 데이터 저장소를 시도하면
thing just with a different vector store imported from Lang Chain, and you might want to give that
랭 체인에서 불러온 다른 벡터 저장소와 같은 겁니다 여러분도 시도해
a try yourself.
보세요
But let me run this one line and it has run.
이 라인을 실행해 볼게요 실행됐네요
And the vector store has been created with 123 documents.
벡터 스토어는 123개의 문서가 만들어졌죠
And that's comforting to know, because 123 was the number of chunks that we had.
그 말을 들으니 안심이 되네요 덩어리 수가 123개였거든요
So it's good that there is indeed a same, uh, number of documents in our vector data store.
벡터 데이터 저장소에 같은 수의 문서가 있다는 건 좋은 일이죠
Um, and the way that we found that, by the way, is that the vector store object that came back from
크롬을 생성하고 돌아온 벡터 스토어 객체를 발견할 수 있었습니다
creating Chrome, we passed in, of course, the chunks, the embeddings, which was the OpenAI embeddings,
덩크와 OpenAI 엠베딩을 전달했습니다 간단하게 데이터베이스의
and then just simply the name of the database.
이름을요
Those were the three things we provided, which makes total sense.
그게 우리가 제공한 3가지예요 완전히 말이 되죠
And that's all that we needed to create our vector store.
벡터 스토어를 생성하는데 필요한 건 그게 다죠
And that vector store we can call underscore collection dot count to get the number of documents in
벡터 스토어는 get_Cetting.Count라고 호출할 수 있습니다 벡터 스토어 내 문서의 수를
the vector store.
얻기 위해서요
So let's just find out how many dimensions these vectors have so we can get a vector from the collection
벡터들의 크기가 얼마나 되는지 알아봅시다. 이것으로 컬렉션으로부터 벡터를 얻을 수 있어요.
So so so the collection is just what you get if you call this underscore collection um uh attribute
그래서 컬렉션은 이 밑줄 get을 호출하면 얻게 되는 거죠 벡터 스토어의
from Vector Store.
특성
So we can then call dot get.
그런 다음 .get을 호출하죠
We can pass in a limit.
한계를 넘을 수 있어요
We only want one.
우린 한 명만 원해요
We want it to bring back the embeddings which is the vector itself.
벡터인 내장들을 불러오길 원하죠
Um, and then we will just have a look at that and let's have a look at how large it is.
그리고 그걸 살펴보고 얼마나 큰지 볼 거예요
It is 1536 dimensions.
1536차원이에요
So 1536 numbers make up this chunk.
1536개의 숫자가 이 덩어리를 이루죠
So let's have a look at this ourselves so we can just just print it.
우리가 직접 보죠 그냥 프린트할 수 있게요
Let's just print sample embedding see what it looks like.
삽입 샘플을 인쇄해서 어떤지 보죠
Wowza.
놀랍네요
It's a lot of numbers.
숫자가 많네요
It's meaningless to to you and me.
당신과 나에겐 무의미해요
Uh, but these numbers in some way.
하지만 이 숫자들은 어떤 식으로든 그래요
We see these numbers in some way reflect the meaning of the chunk that they're associated with.
이 숫자들은 어떤 식으로든 숫자와 관련된 덩어리의 의미를 반영해요
And we'll see.
두고 봐야죠
We'll associate it with a chunk in just a second.
잠시 후 덩어리랑 연결시켜 보죠
So it's a ton of numbers.
숫자가 엄청나요
It's 1536 numbers, which we can interpret as representing a coordinate in 1536 dimensional space.
1536개의 숫자로 1536차원 공간의 좌표를 해석할 수 있어요
Um, and that that coordinate is chosen such that other other vectors that have a similar coordinate
그 좌표가 선택되면 비슷한 좌표를 가진 다른 벡터들이 벡터 공간에서
that are close in vector space should have similar meaning.
비슷한 의미를 갖는 거죠
That's the whole idea behind this.
그게 이 요리의 핵심이죠
So let's take a moment to visualize this.
잠시 시각화해 보죠
That's going to be a nice, uh, get rid of some of these comments.
댓글을 없애면 좋을 것 같아요 Get it
This will be some nice, uh, um, uh, a nice way to, to be able to really investigate what's going
좋은 방법이 될 거예요 무대 뒤에서 무슨 일이 일어나는지 제대로 조사할 수 있는
on behind the scenes.
방법이죠
So you can call Collectiongetty and ask for the embeddings, the documents and the metadata, like this.
컬렉션겟티에 전화해 메타데이터와 문서 내장 정보를 요청할 수 있어요
And once I've done that, I can put the vectors.
일단 그렇게 하고 나면 벡터들을 put 할 수 있어요
I can take the embeddings and put them into an array of vectors, and I can take the the doc types and
박아둔 것들을 벡터들의 배열에 넣을 수 있습니다. doc 타입을 doc 타입이라는 것에
put that into something called doc types.
넣을 수 있어요.
And then I'm going to make some some colors up as you will see.
이제 색을 좀 만들어 볼게요
So this is just some pre-work to get ready.
Get it get get it 사전 작업이에요
Now there's one problem that we have is that, uh, as human beings have a deficiency, that we have
한 가지 문제가 있습니다 인간은 결점이 있는데 모든 걸 3차원 이상으로
a problem visualizing anything in more than three dimensions.
시각화하는 데 문제가 있다는 거죠
So visualizing something in 1536 dimensions is going to be very challenging indeed.
1536차원으로 시각화하는 건 정말 어려운 일이에요
Um, but luckily there are various techniques we can use to do what they call projecting down or trying
다행히 다양한 기술을 활용할 수 있어요 하향 투사라는 걸 하는데 차원을
to, uh, reduce the dimensions to only, let's say, two dimensions in a way that does the best possible
2차원으로만 축소하는 거죠 그렇게 하면 사물을 분리하는 데 가장 효과적인
job at separating things out to stay faithful to the, the, uh, multi-dimensional representation.
방법으로 다차원적 표현에 충실할 수 있어요
So trying to do it in a way that is going to have things that are further apart in all of these dimensions
그래서 모든 면에서 좀 더 멀리 떨어져 있는 걸 만들려 하면 2차원으로
will still be fairly far apart, even when it's projected down to two dimensions.
투사했을 때도 여전히 꽤 멀리 떨어져 있을 거예요
That's the idea.
그게 목적이죠
There are various techniques for doing it that are not going to go into, but the one that we're going
그에 대한 다양한 기술이 있지만 자세히 다루진 않겠습니다만 저희가 사용할
to use is extremely common.
기술은 아주 일반적인 거죠
It's called t-SNE, which stands for T-distributed Stochastic Neighbor embedding, and is one of those
t-SNE라고 하는데 T 분산 가설 이웃 침투의 약자죠 구글에 검색하거나
ones that you can Google or ask ChatGPT if you want an explanation behind it.
설명을 듣고 싶을 때 챗GPT에 물어보면 나오는 거예요
Um, so we pass into it, how many dimensions do we want?
통과할 때 몇 가지 차원을 원하죠?
We want it projected down from the thousand and whatever to two dimensions.
천 가지에서 2차원으로 영사하는 거죠
And this random state is a way of setting its random seed so that each time we call this, we get the
이 무작위 상태는 무작위 씨앗을 설정하는 방식이에요 이걸 호출할 때마다 같은
same thing so that we can reproduce this.
결과가 나와서 이걸 재생산할 수 있죠 get it
Um, and then you can get your reduced vectors just by calling the fit transform method on this t-SNE
그러면 감소된 벡터를 얻을 수 있습니다. t-SNE 객체에 대한 get transform 메서드를 호출하면요.
Um, what I'm then doing is I'm using the fabulous library plotly to make a nice scatter diagram.
이제 멋진 라이브러리 플리틀리를 이용해서 멋진 분산 도표를 만들 거예요
Um, And, you know, this is all sort of this kind of code that you can copy and paste and reuse as
이건 전부 일종의 코드예요 원하는 대로 복사, 붙여넣기, 재사용할 수
you wish.
있죠
But I've got some nice things like I'm making the markers have different colors based on the colors
하지만 멋진 걸 했어요 마커에 다른 색을 입혔죠 다양한
that we set here for the different document types, and also got some pop up text which is going to
문서 유형에 맞춰 설정한 색에 근거해서요 팝업 텍스트도 있어요
actually have a fragment, the first 100 characters from the chunk itself.
청크 자체에서 첫 100개의 글자가 조각으로 나오죠
So what we're hoping to see here is we're hoping to see how do the documents look in the vector database.
여기서 보고 싶은 건 문서가 벡터 데이터베이스에서 어떻게 보이는지 보는 거예요
And then for each of these different vectors, we're going to color it by what kind of document is it.
그런 다음 각각의 다른 벡터에 대해 어떤 종류의 문서인지에 따라 색을 입힐 거예요
And it's going to have hover over text.
텍스트 위로 마우스가 떠요
So we can actually read a little bit of the fragment of text that this chunk represents.
이 비트 조각이 나타내는 텍스트 조각을 읽을 수 있어요
So we'll see if this works.
잘 되는지 보죠
That would be quite cool.
그럼 멋지겠네요
Of course I know it works.
당연히 알죠
I've already tried it.
이미 해 봤어요
Here it is.
여기 있네요
Okay.
네
So what are we looking at.
이게 뭐죠?
So we're looking at a visualization of the multi-dimensional vectors projected down to 2D for us, there's
다차원 벡터의 시각화를 보고 있는데 2D로 보여줍니다 엑스 축과 Y축의
no particular meaning of the x axis and the y axis.
특별한 의미가 없어요
It's just the best possible way of spreading out the different points.
여러 지점을 분산시킬 수 있는 최선의 방법이죠
Now there's a few things to notice.
몇 가지 알아두셔야 할 게 있어요
The green dots that you see here are representing employees.
여기 보이는 녹색 점들은 직원들을 나타내요
The red dots are representing.
빨간 점은 뭘 의미할까요?
And when I say employees I mean they're representing chunks of text plucked out of employee documents.
여기서 직원이라는 건 직원 문서에서 텍스트를 잔뜩 뽑아낸다는 뜻이에요
The red things are chunks of text coming out of contracts.
빨간 건 계약서에서 나온 텍스트 덩어리예요
The blue are from product documentation and the yellow is from about documents.
파란색은 제품 문서화 노란색은 어바웃 문서화예요
Now, there's something a bit magical that you have to to appreciate, to realize at this point when
이 시점에서 아셔야 할 마법 같은 게 있어요 OpenAI가 비트를
the OpenAI embeddings, when when it was vectorizing these chunks of text, it did not know the document
삽입할 때 텍스트 덩어리를 벡터화할 때 문서 유형을 몰랐어요
type.
메타데이터는 말 안 했어요
We didn't we didn't tell it that summer employees, summer products and summer contracts.
여름철 직원, 여름철 제품 여름철 계약에 대해 말하지 않았어요
We just gave it the chunk of text and said, turn this into a vector.
텍스트 덩어리를 주고 벡터로 바꾸라고 했죠
And so that's all it had.
그게 다였어요
Um, and so it's kind of magical that based on those chunks, these chunks have been separated out in
그 덩어리들을 바탕으로 보면 이 덩어리들이 벡터 공간으로 분리되어
vector space and they occupy different distinct regions in space.
공간 내의 다른 영역을 차지하고 있어요
Um, because they're somewhat similar to each other in terms of the content, the meaning of what they
서로 어느 정도 비슷하거든요 내용이나 의미 면에서요
represent, the employees are all kind of in the same general territory.
직원들은 모두 같은 영역에 있어요
The, the, the contracts are over here and the products are here.
계약서는 여기 있고 제품은 여기 있어요
You may notice that some of the contract information appears to be more a sort of a, uh, in the same
일부 계약 정보가 제품과 같은 부근에 있는 걸 눈치채셨을
vicinity as the products.
거예요
And that might be surprising for a moment.
잠시 놀라실지도 모르겠네요
It might look like maybe something's gone wrong.
뭔가 잘못된 것처럼 보일 수도 있어요
But no, if you hover over these chunks, you'll see that this is the particular chunk of text in a
이 덩어리들을 마우스로 가리키면 계약의 특정 텍스트 덩어리란 걸 알 수 있어요
contract, which describes the key features that that client has signed up for.
클라이언트가 등록한 핵심 기능을 설명하는 거죠
And you can see there it says type the text in there.
텍스트를 입력하라고 하는 게 보이시죠
Sorry if I if I hover for a moment where you see that second line where it says text, that is the extract
죄송합니다 잠시 마우스로 가리켜보면 텍스트라는 두 번째 줄이 있는데 벡터 공간에 있는
from the chunk that has been put in that location in vector space, and you'll see that it starts features
위치에 있는 덩어리를 추출한 것입니다. 하나의 인공지능으로 된 매칭을
one AI powered matching.
볼 수 있는데요.
And let's find another one here.
다른 걸 찾아보죠
Uh, AI powered risk assessment features.
인공지능 위험 평가 기능이죠
It's the same thing.
그게 그거죠
Um, so what we're seeing here is that within contracts, there is some information that is more like
여기서 보이는 건 계약 안에 기능성 정보 같은 게 있어요
And that functionality lives in vector space in a similar kind of space to other product information.
기능성 물질은 벡터 공간에 존재합니다 다른 제품과 비슷한 공간에 존재하죠
So, uh, hopefully that makes sense.
이해가 되셨으면 좋겠네요
It's again, it's almost spooky how good it is at kind of associating the right location in space to
다시 말씀드리지만 공간의 올바른 위치를 문서의 의미와 연결하는 건 거의 소름
the meaning behind the document.
끼칠 정도로 잘하죠
And the final point I'll mention, and I might be I might be putting, uh, putting taking this too
마지막으로 말씀드릴 요점은 너무 멀리 간 것일 수도 있지만 제가
far, but it really seems to me like this is what's going on.
보기엔 이런 상황 같아요
You'll notice that the three documents that are about the company.
보시면 회사 관련 서류가 세 장 있어요
Uh, these three here are kind of in the center.
여기 이 세 개가 중앙에 있어요
They're right in the middle between all these different documents.
여러 문서들 가운데에 있어요
And I think that's because it kind of encompasses some information that pertains to the employees and
그건 일부 정보를 포함하고 있기 때문이라고 봅니다
the contracts and the, the, the, the product as well.
직원과 계약 제품과 관련된 정보요
Uh, it's kind of central information that that is related to everything.
모든 것과 관련된 중심 정보 같은 거죠
And that's why it's somehow in a sort of place that is in the middle of all of the rest of the information.
그래서 이 모든 게 어떤 식으로든 모든 정보의 한가운데에 있는 거죠 REST
Um, so I find that fascinating.
그게 참 흥미로워요
I might be reading too much into it, but it does seem that way to me.
내가 오버하는 걸 수도 있지만 그런 것 같아요
Uh, and one of the things that you can do is just experiment with putting any chunks of text that you
여러분이 할 수 있는 것 중 하나는 벡터 데이터베이스에 넣고 싶은 텍스트 덩어리를
want into the vector database.
실험해보는 거예요
You can just imagine you can just go back and add in other documents, uh, into the documents that
돌아가서 다른 문서를 추가할 수 있다고 상상해 보세요 여기 로드한 문서에
we load here.
말이죠
Either you can just specify a file directly, or you can just put in some more text or just add text
파일을 직접 지정하거나 텍스트를 추가하거나 기존
into the existing documents and then see where they end up in vector space, and use that as a way of
문서에 텍스트를 추가해서 벡터 공간으로 보내거나 둘 중 하나입니다.
really getting to appreciate, uh, the the way that OpenAI embeddings is able to understand the meaning
그리고 이것을 통해 오픈AI가 다른 텍스트의 의미를 이해하고 비슷한
behind a different chunk of text and position that in a way that is, that is closest to other things
의미의 다른 것들에 가깝게 배치할 수 있다는 것을 알게 되었는데요.
And that's that's the whole idea.
그게 핵심이에요
Well, this 2D representation was was really cool.
이 2D 모형은 정말 멋졌어요
Uh, is there anything better than a 2D representation?
2D 표현보다 더 좋은 게 있을까요?
Of course there is.
당연히 있죠
There's a 3D representation and that's what we're going to do next.
3D 표현이 있어요 그게 다음에 할 일이죠
Uh, we're going to try 3D because it's just as simple as turning that number two into a number three,
3D로 해보죠 간단하거든요 2를 3으로 바꾸는 것만큼요
and we will then be able to visualize these vectors in 3D.
그럼 3D의 이 벡터를 시각화할 수 있어요
It wasn't quite that simple.
그렇게 간단하지 않았어요
I also had to put a 3D in here, and I had to mess around with with some other vectors and all of that
여기에 3D도 넣어야 했어요. 다른 벡터들도 만져야 했죠. 하지만
stuff, but it's pretty similar.
꽤 비슷해요.
And I had to change the title from 2D to 3D as well.
타이틀도 2D에서 3D로 바꿔야 했어요
Anyway, let's see how this looks.
어쨌든, 어떤지 보죠
Here it is.
여기 있네요
Um, so these are our vectors projected not all the way down to 2D, but now to 3D.
이게 벡터예요 2D에서 3D로 영사된 거죠
Um, and the first thing you might notice is that actually, this is one of those rare times, uh,
첫 번째로 눈치챌 수 있는 건 사실 아주 드문 경우라는 거예요
a bit like movies that, uh, 3D isn't necessarily better than 2D.
영화처럼 3D가 2D보다 나을 때도 있어요 비트 비트
Uh, that, uh, it does look a little bit more of a of a jumble.
비트가 좀 뒤죽박죽인 것 같네요
It's a bit harder to to see.
비트는 잘 안 보여요
It does look again like the yellow is in the middle.
노란색이 가운데 있는 것처럼 보이긴 해요
Uh, and green, red and blue are clearly separated out.
초록, 빨강, 파랑은 확실히 구분돼 있고요
But there are some, um, that have combined, as you would expect, as we saw before.
하지만 예상하셨듯이 일부 요소가 합쳐졌어요
But the nice thing about this is we can, uh, actively, uh, we can interactively play with this.
이 제품의 장점은 상호 작용적으로 놀 수 있다는 거예요
We can rotate it like this.
이렇게 돌릴 수 있어요
Isn't that something?
대단하지 않아요?
And we can use this to get a better sense of how they are laid out.
이걸 이용해서 어떻게 배치됐는지 더 잘 알 수 있어요 get get get get it
And it does give you a nice sense that there is a distinction between them.
둘 사이에 차이가 있다는 걸 알 수 있죠
Um, but I do have to admit that it's not perhaps as clear as the 2D representation.
하지만 2D 묘사만큼 명확하진 않은 것 같아요
Uh, but nonetheless, it looks great.
그래도 보기 좋아요
If we hover, you get to see the meaning behind the points.
Get up 하면 포인트 뒤에 있는 의미가 보이시죠?
Of course, as before, the yellow is the about, which does seem to be somewhat in the middle of everything,
물론 아까처럼 노란색은 어바웃입니다 모든 것의 중간에 있는 것처럼
uh, consistent with the point I was making before, uh, this blue one here is a bit of an outlier.
보이죠 아까 말씀드린 것과 일치합니다 여기 이 파란색은 좀 특이하죠
Um, and, uh, yeah, you, uh, you can certainly have fun with the 3D representation, although perhaps
3D로 표현한 비트도 충분히 즐길 수 있어요 2D가 어떤 면에서는
the 2D one is a bit more clear in some ways.
더 명확하긴 하지만요
Anyway, that concludes our playing with vectors, but there's a big takeaway, which is now it's over
벡터 실험은 이걸로 끝났는데 중요한 게 있어요 이제 여러분에게 달렸다는 거죠 이
to you, not just about looking at these diagrams and inspecting the different chunks of text, but
도표를 보고 텍스트의 다양한 덩어리를 검사하는 게 아니라 자신의 텍스트 덩어리를
adding your own chunks of text.
추가하는 거예요
Simple way to do it is just to put things documents into the knowledge, into the knowledge base directory.
간단한 방법은 문서를 지식 저장소에 넣는 겁니다 지식 기반 디렉터리에 말이에요 Put
You can just do that and it will just work right away.
그렇게만 하면 바로 효과가 나타나죠
But you can also play around with the text loader classes to add in chunks using lang chains code instead
텍스트 로더 클래스도 활용할 수 있어요 문서를 그냥 드롭하는 대신 랑가인 코드를 이용해 청크를
of just dropping a document in there.
추가하는 거죠
But when you've put your chunks in, see where they end up in vector space and get a sense of how that
하지만 덩어리들을 넣고 나면 벡터 공간에서 어디에 도달하는지 보고 어떻게 작동하는지 감을 잡으세요 Get in get in
works.
get
Or you can replace the whole knowledge base directory, rename that to something else, create a new
또는 전체 지식 기반 디렉터리를 대체할 수도 있습니다 다른 것으로 이름을
directory and just fill it with some some very simple things just so you can experiment with seeing
바꾸고 새 디렉터리를 생성해 아주 간단한 것으로 채우는 거죠 문서가 벡터 스페이스 내 다른 위치에
how documents get put into different locations in vector space.
어떻게 놓이는지 실험할 수 있도록요 Get up Get up
And that's super important homework because it's going to give you a good basis for the next part,
아주 중요한 숙제예요 다음 단계에 대한 기반을 제공하거든요 실제로
which is when we get to rag for real.
Get을 하는 단계요
First, let's go back to the slides.
먼저 슬라이드로 돌아가죠